Finding Aid for Michigan Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights Records, 1974-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights Records 1974-1993
Michigan Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights
0.5 linear ft.
9416 Bj 2
Michigan chapter of organization of religious groups devoted to safeguarding access to legal abortion. Administrative files include minutes, financial records, lists, and policy and program committee reports; publicity and outreach files include news releases, clippings, newsletters, and other informational materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the Michigan Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights (Donor No. 8189 ) in October 1993.
The record group is closed except with the written permission of the organization's director or chairman of the board, or of the director of the Michigan ACLU.
The Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights (RCAR) is a national organization of religious groups which is devoted to safeguarding access to legal abortion. RCAR was formed by leaders from 31 predominantly Protestant and Jewish groups in the wake of the 1973 Roe v. Wade Supreme Court decision which legalized abortion. The Michigan chapter of RCAR was established in June 1975, and members include organizations as well as individual clergy and laypeople. RCAR supports women's right to choose abortion as an expression of religious freedom. The group believes that it is a violation of women's freedom of religion for the state to impose restrictions on their ability to follow their own conscience and faith regarding abortion. In addition to actively promoting separation of church and state, and freedom of reproductive choice, RCAR encourages sex education and family planning.
Since the 1970s, members of Michigan RCAR have published newsletters and legislative updates, lobbied in Lansing and Washington, and organized letter writing campaigns, rallies, conferences, and other pro-choice events. The group is a non-profit organization which is run by an Executive Director and Policy Council consisting of representatives from a variety of religious groups. Michigan RCAR relies on donations and the efforts of volunteers to accomplish its goals.
The papers of the Michigan Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights are arranged in two series, Administration, and Publicity and Outreach.
Subjects:
Abortion--Law and legislation--Michigan.; Michigan Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights.
- Administration
  The Administration series provides information about Michigan RCAR's internal organization, mainly since the mid-1980s. The minutes from Policy Council and Director's Reports contain yearly summations of the group's activities, and give some sense how priorities were set and activities were planned. The "Policy Council and Affiliated Pro-choice Group Lists" folder provides information about the founding of the Michigan chapter of RCAR in 1975.
  - Bylaws, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Financial Reports, 1986-1989 (Box 1)
  - Financial Support from Organizations, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Minutes-Policy Council, 1985-1988, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Minutes and Director's Report, 1989-1990, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Policy and Program Committee Reports, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Policy Council and Affiliated Pro-choice Group Lists, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
- Publicity and Outreach
  The Publicity AND Outreach series contains information about the group's public activities, including early publications from RCAR's national office (RCAR Dispatch, RCAR State Letters), Legislative Information Sheets, and the Michigan RCAR newsletter "Choice". The series also includes the organization's press releases and informational handouts, as well as newspaper clippings about the group. The series also contains records of fundraising and publicity events such as the annual State Fair booth and a 1989 Mother's Day celebration.
  - Legislative Alerts, 1979-1986 (Box 1)
  - Legislative Information Sheets, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Mother's Day Events, 1989 (Box 1)
  - News Releases and Handouts, 1974-1987 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings and Press Releases re: Proposal A, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings and Letters to the Editor, 1989 (Box 1)
  - RCAR Dispatch, 1975-1978 (Box 1)
  - RCAR State Letters #10-#37, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - State Fair Booth, 1990 (Box 1)